The armed conflicts that marked the 20th and early 21st centuries all have a root,
even tenuous,
in the treaties and the fragile peace of 1919.
They are like skipping stones,
the convulsions,
The epilogues of a century-old story.
Why is the Middle East today?
Are Sarajevo still places of tension and conflict?
All of that,
It evokes events and tensions that took place during the First World War.
When we look at all the margins of the current European Union,
We realize that they correspond to all those areas of fracture and rupture in which treaties failed to provide positive solutions at the end of the First World War.
Sarajevo,
Bosnia and Herzegovina.
A commercial crossroads since time immemorial,
a cosmopolitan city where religions live together.
This is the Jerusalem of the Balkans,
where over less than 500 meters,
The mosque is next to the synagogue.
the Orthodox Church,
the cathedral.
It all started in this small town.
Here, on June 28, 1914,
a Serbian student from Bosnia,
Gavrilo Princip,
unwittingly triggered a global catastrophe by assassinating Archduke Franz Ferdinand.
heir to the throne of the Austro-Hungarian Empire.
It is 11 a.m.
when, after a first failed attack,
Principe is located on the boulevard,
just around the corner.
The car stops there.
As fate would have it, François Ferdinand arrived at the feet of the man who would kill him a few seconds later.
Principe was a young nationalist who dreamed of the creation of a unified Yugoslavia.
For him,
François Ferdinand,
to embody the empire,
evil,
the occupation,
All,
It is simply the act of someone who dreamed of freedom, Yugoslavia, and justice.
To pull meant to free oneself.
Sarajevo was in a way the triggering event of the First World War.
In fact, the symbolic starting point with this assassination had consequences throughout the world.
It is the result of a very local context and the emergence of nationalism or the beginning of a national sentiment of the struggle for the creation of a new state.
This small, local winter event led to,
through the system of alliances,
one of the world's greatest conflicts.
1917.
After three years of pointless slaughter and assaults,
The Americans go to war.
A game changer,
and give a second wind to the allied troops.
For an American who is fighting,
six men in the rear in logistics.
200,000 per day.
The advantage was quickly regained against the Germans, who failed to retake Paris.
At the end of the summer of 1918,
the latest German offensives on the French front
They all failed.
Foch launched a general offensive across the entire Allied front, pushing the Germans back towards their borders.
towards the borders of Belgium,
by forcing them to evacuate all the regions that have been occupied since the fall
1914. At the end of 1918,
The German army is exhausted.
Everyone in the army knows that you can't win the war.
We know it's not going to go well.
But no one can say how long the front will hold.
And from the summer of 1918,
The hope of victory no longer resonates with the population.
We continue because we have no other choice.
But there is hunger in the homes.
We no longer understand this war.
We don't want this war anymore.
German soldiers surrender by the thousands and mutinies break out.
From that moment on,
The soldiers will simply return home and no one will forcibly bring them back to the front.
because the command structure is no longer working very well.
And it is in this atmosphere that sailors' strikes will break out in Wilhelmshaven and Kiel.
And in two or three days,
This movement is growing so large that 30,000 men,
as many as 40,000 men will demonstrate in the streets chanting "Thank you".
The war is over.
On the Allied side,
This is the moment of the decisive battle.
There is no breakthrough in the strict sense of the Hindenburg Line.
The Germans' last line of defense, or defense system,
There is an almost arithmetic pressure exerted on the entire front, and it is the power of the Allied economy and industry that is forcing the German army to retreat and evacuate all the territories it occupied.
With, for the first time, the use of a new weapon.
The tank-aircraft pairing,
Pétain used it for the first time.
during the month of July 1918 to stop the last German offensives.
In Germany,
The situation is catastrophic.
The allies have imposed a food blockade.
For civilians,
It's already unbearable when hunger is added to a difficult daily life.
The children have nothing left to eat.
The women send letters to their husbands at the front asking them to send food to Germany.
And that's what men did.
And it is very clear that the brutality of the German occupiers in northern France and the mass requisitions were commensurate with what they lacked at home.
Strikes break out every day.
Throughout Germany,
Bolshevik ideas are gaining ground and shaking the Empire.
The Red Revolution is on the verge of succeeding.
The beginning of November,
There is this revolution in Germany,
And of course we fear that it will be the same scenario as in Russia.
SO,
We were fed up with the ending.
and with the end,
We were fed up with the war.
German public opinion has had enough.
The general staff must face the facts.
We must request an armistice.
Hindenburg and Ludendorff,
the two leaders of the German army,
they say,
We are lost.
We are retreating on the French front.
Our safety is no longer guaranteed.
We need to get out of this war as quickly as possible.
From October 1918,
Talks begin with Wilson,
the President of the United States,
who has a big project in mind.
To propose peace,
just,
based on 14 points that will revolutionize future international relations.
The Germans see this as an opportunity for an honorable end to the conflict.
Starting in September-October,
We are talking about Wilson's peace.
It gives German democrats a tiny bit of hope that they could achieve a good peace and that the new system will lead to a good peace.
As a result,
the wish that the war must end,
that Wilson's peace must come about,
will become very prominent.
Very quickly,
The French, the British, and the Italians are furious.
because they feel we weren't consulted.
They set their conditions.
They make Wilson understand,
Why not use the 14-point system as a base?
But security still needs to be ensured.
in particular the security of France.
The Germans made contact for the armistice via radio.
The Germans will be allowed,
politicians and military personnel united,
to cross French lines and reach a forest,
Why? To be safe.
the French.
And this forest was not chosen by chance.
It is located near Sanlis,
where Marshal Foch has his headquarters.
It's at Rotonde,
in a clearing,
near a railway intersection,
that the ceasefire will be signed.
This is the first time Marshal Foch has seen the German plenipotentiaries.
At Rotonde,
This was three days before the signing of the armistice.
It's November 8th.
Marshal Foch had the German plenipotentiaries sit in the carriage and asked them innocently what the purpose of their visit was.
Then the German commissioners got a little confused and said, "Listen,
We've come to see what the proposals are.
And the marshal said, "But I have no proposal to make to you."
So he rephrases their question
"What are the conditions of the armistice?"
Ah!
You ask for an armistice and he takes the sheet of paper out of his pocket and tells them the conditions of the armistice.
The atmosphere was fine,
nothing more.
In other words, Marshal Foch was dry.
There's no discussion.
You have come to ask for an armistice,
Yes or no.
Until the bells rang at 11 a.m. on the 11th,
It's an armistice that will be secret.
Even though the military considers that it has not suffered a defeat,
These are German civilians who are concluding four years of war and accepting,
almost surreptitiously,
armistice conditions under humiliating circumstances.
What,
if it was not intentional,
sows the seeds of revenge.
The armistice was imposed on the Germans with very harsh military conditions.
but which correspond to the current situation.
Very harsh conditions allow,
From a French perspective,
Two things.
A,
if the Germans accept them,
to put them in a position that no longer allows them to resume the war.
If they refuse them,
well...
The Allied arithmetic machine will continue to crush the German army.
It's over.
In the streets of Paris and elsewhere,
The people rejoice.
The soldiers are relieved to be alive.
Belgium and northern France are now nothing but ruins.
Villages in the East have been wiped off the map.
But the victory of the allies is not the victory of peace.
Europe must be rebuilt on the ruins of three empires, and this must be settled once and for all.
it is believed,
the fate of Germany.
June 28, 1919,
7 months later.
It's a beautiful midday in Versailles.
A little chilly.
The area around the castle is packed with people.
Throughout the next 3 hours,
Everything was carefully chosen to humiliate the Germans again.
The place?
Versailles and its Hall of Mirrors,
a symbol of French diplomacy,
where the German Empire was born in 1871.
The date?
Five years to the day after the Sarajevo assassination,
pretext for the Great War.
Men?
The disfigured faces,
placed along the route of the Germans before going to sign.
The Hall of Mirrors is crowded.
But the Germans are not here.
They arrive through a hidden door, out of sight.
The German delegation arrived through this door which leads into Madame Victoire's large study.
And from this piece,
She then enters the castle.
She walks through the last rooms of Madame Victoire's apartment,
crosses the Queen's grand apartment to emerge at the entrance to the Hall of Mirrors.
This journey is actually a practical one.
It was absolutely essential to prevent the German delegation from following the same route as the Allied delegations which,
they,
entered directly through the royal court.
But it is certain that the German delegation was to be confronted with the full force of French history.
if I may say so
in the Hall of Mirrors itself,
because this is the grand decor of Louis XIV which magnifies the victories of France against Germany.
3 p.m.
Clemenceau,
surrounded by Lloyd George Langlais and the American Wilson,
takes place around a desk,
extracted for the occasion from the national furniture collection.
So this office was actually located at the almost geometric center of the gallery.
We are getting closer,
Here we are in the center.
He was there,
with an armchair placed with its back to the windows.
So the person signing was facing powerful allies who were behind that long table which was in front of the mirrors.
Silence falls.
We get the Germans to sign first, just to be on the safe side.
The representatives of the Weimar Republic,
Muller and Bell,
Pale and Malay,
look,
according to the Figaro columnist,
of two workers dressed in their Sunday best.
The Minister of Foreign Affairs,
the representative of Germany,
refused to use one of the pens provided since they were pens that had been donated by veterans' associations, and so he used his own fountain pen.
Moreover, it was a treaty that no one on the German side wanted to sign.
We had to find two.
of ministers,
of volunteers
if I may say so
to come and sign.
The Germans were naturally humiliated from the start.
The first humiliation,
And we often forget that,
It's because they've been forgotten.
excluded from peace negotiations.
When on January 18, 1919,
Discussions to reach Versailles have begun.
There are 27 nations,
but no nation defeated.
And that,
throughout the history of treaties,
That had never happened before.
The Germans are,
We know this from testimonies,
on the verge of tears.
And it's an extremely difficult time.
extremely painful.
And I don't think they appreciated it very much.
In any case, they took advantage of the setting that was available to them.
There is also that incredible scene when the German delegation was led to Versailles.
Before,
They had been led into the destroyed territories,
and they burst into tears when they saw what the war had destroyed there.
And the French told them,
It wasn't the war that destroyed all of that.
You're the one who destroyed all of this.
And even today,
It's unbearable to think that we destroyed all of that.
But that's how it is.
We are responsible for everything.
An hour and a half later,
It's all over.
The Germans are the first to come out.
Then it's the collue.
We run through the gardens of Versailles, following the cars.
Peace has been made.
We have found Alsace.
We sing the Marseillaise.
But before the signing of the Treaty of Versailles,
for six months,
between January and June 1919,
between negotiations,
compromise,
threats...
Three men changed the world.
The Allies may have won the war,
They now need to achieve a lasting peace.
French and English speakers began discussing things immediately after November 11th.
But we have to wait for Wilson.
who arrives in Europe with 14 points,
as a basis for discussion.
Wilson was born in the middle of the
19th century,
in the southern United States.
He becomes its president.
Wilson was the child of a pastor.
He knew the Scriptures by heart, of course.
He said his prayers every day.
He was extremely religious.
He wanted to save the world with the values ​​of Christ.
He identified with Christ.
He believed that America was a gift from God.
Wilson knows the Gospel according to America.
With his grand idea,
the right of peoples to self-determination.
To play the people rather than the governments.
Nations rather than empires, and preventing war.
To sell its 14 points,
He embarks on a triumphant tour of Europe.
Wilson is the only US president who spends six months living abroad.
He lives in Paris for 6 months.
His house is called the temporary white house.
When he arrives in France,
No one has ever been welcomed like this before.
In Italy,
all women,
The men have candles.
No statesman in the entire history of the world has been received.
in the world,
in the days following the armistice,
as Wilson is received.
And so it goes to his head a little.
For six months,
Paris will settle future international relations.
The capital is becoming cosmopolitan.
A thousand American citizens are settling in Le Crayon,
transformed into warships.
200 English people at the Majestic Hotel,
Clébert Avenue,
The Italians towards the opera house,
We have dinner,
We're going to the theatre.
We meet at the cafe.
The negotiations taking place in Paris bring together 32 countries.
Paris is the center of the world.
Paris,
It is not only the center of world diplomacy in 19,
but it is the accelerated training school for the world's leaders who will rule for the next 30 or 40 years.
The peace conference,
It was the place to be at that moment.
The conference that is about to begin is dominating all conversations.
Four nations to negotiate,
Italy,
France,
the United States and Great Britain.
British Prime Minister Lloyd George does not want to leave too much room for France on the new chessboard.
He had the ambition to remain in power and to promote the interests of the British Empire.
He doesn't give a damn about humanity as a whole.
And he is the one who will be most successful in the negotiation.
He was incredible.
He managed to get everything he wanted by using his skills and tactics.
playing Clemenceau against
Wilson, Wilson versus Clemenceau.
He was managing.
For the first time in European history,
We will negotiate amongst ourselves.
It's a veritable monologue from the victors.
conditions to be imposed.
to the vanquished.
The third man,
It's Clemenceau.
76 years old,
former doctor,
formerly a journalist,
He is the French war hero.
The father of victory,
synonymous with strength and patriotism.
In this game,
Clemenceau has adversaries.
His name is
Lloyd George and his name is
Wilson, to a lesser degree,
Orlando.
What interests him,
It is the defense and security of France.
Nothing else mattered to him.
He is old.
He is 80 years old.
Him,
He doesn't want France to be invaded again by Germany.
He wants security.
etc.
He didn't...
His career is behind him.
Yes, indeed.
There is also a battle of egos.
The four-way discussions began in the offices of the Quai d'Orsay.
We need to find our rhythm against Wilson.
who is against a kind of club of powers.
He wants to involve all the victors in the negotiations.
always supporting,
and from the very beginning,
his idea of ​​a society of nations.
Am I to understand that no decision will be made without the opinion of Costa Rica or Brazil?
Meanwhile,
behind the scenes and late into the night,
52 committees composed of experts are hard at work,
including the one that deals with redrawing the borders of new countries emerging from fallen empires.
There were general principles that had been established, and then the precise division was made, for example, according to economic criteria.
ethnic and political criteria.
Everything related to communication,
transportation,
resources,
It was all about finding the right balance.
SO,
we examined the border between Chepania and Saros-Patag.
It therefore goes without saying that the junction
Miskovec-Cascao, along with Saint-Péter-Lonzon, will have to pass through here and is awarded to...
The work of these commissions enabled the viability of new European states.
like Czechoslovakia.
The Treaty of Versailles was one of the decisive steps in the creation of Czechoslovakia after the First World War.
When the Czechoslovak conference opened,
Peace,
The legitimacy of the new state is already accepted.
So it was quite obvious,
when discussing the implementation of independence,
that we were going to base ourselves on historical borders.
These borders are still relevant today.
These are the same relations we still have with Germany today.
Austria and Poland.
But the peace conference sweeps this under the rug,
from the very beginning,
with the drawing of the borders,
an essential piece of information that will be,
20 years later,
explosive.
Minorities.
The Sudetenland region is predominantly populated by Germans.
For Czechoslovakia,
There is an additional problem.
That's because of the entire Northwest,
The West and Southwest have a German population.
And this German population,
That's not insignificant.
Czechs are clearly the majority in Czechoslovakia.
The second nation,
These are the Sudetes.
The Slovaks only come in third position.
So it's not insignificant.
Czechoslovakia did its best to take into account the needs of each people.
The protection of minorities has been exemplary.
This has been acknowledged by everyone.
But there was opposition to the establishment of a Czechoslovak state against which we could do nothing.
And this was the great strength of German nationalism, which was exploited by the Nazis.
Hitler did indeed use the Sudetenland case to trigger the beginnings of the Second World War.
The Czechoslovak case tends to be seen as a failure.
For what ?
Because we know how the story ends.
The peace conference then tackled another burning issue.
The partitioning of the former Ottoman Empire.
Emir Faisal is in Paris to discuss what the English have more or less promised him.
An independence for the Arab peoples,
Iraq,
Syria,
Lebanon,
Kuwait,
Palestine,
within a federation.
A state is promised to the Kurds.
At the end,
French and English divide the Middle East into zones of influence.
For their part,
The Italians are impatient.
Orlando has been part of all discussions since early January as an ally.
Victor Emmanuel Orlando was the chairman of the council.
He had made a decisive contribution to the Italian victory.
Orlando tried to get from Wilson what had been agreed upon between the French,
British and Italian,
the 1915 treaty which had motivated Italy's entry into the war,
namely that Dalmatia would be Italian,
that the 31st would be taken from Austria-Hungary and become Italian,
that Fiume would become Italian.
Italy gave the...
Italy wanted to reunify all the populations of Italian origin who had been scattered within the Austro-Hungarian Empire.
It was also an economic problem.
The port of Fiume was a competing port to Trieste.
Under Yugoslav control,
It would have competed with Italy.
An ideal base in the Balkans,
But nothing goes as planned.
Wilson flatly refused.
And in the name of the principle of nationality,
where Wilson was uncompromising,
There is no question of Dalmatia being Italian.
The French are very embarrassed because Italy is their ally.
but at the same time,
They have links with the Serbs and Croats who want to create a Yugoslav state.
And so, obviously, Dalmatia will become Yugoslavian.
And so the French are somewhat torn between the Italians and the Yugoslavs,
and finally make Orlando understand that...
that Dalmatia will become part of Yugoslavia.
As Wilson's sympathy and support for the new Yugoslav state became apparent,
The possibility of reaching an agreement has receded.
Orlando bristles and feels humiliated by the attitude of the other three, who are also using diplomatic tactics.
the language.
Clemenceau spent 5 years in the United States,
when he was 25 years old,
He married an American woman.
He speaks and writes perfect English.
So he doesn't need an interpreter.
They can,
with him and Lloyd George,
to speak English during negotiations.
And this marginalizes the Italian who,
him,
doesn't speak English and doesn't speak French very well either.
Orlando,
poor man
was seen crying because he could not satisfy an increasingly nationalist Italian public opinion, convinced that Italy's contribution to the Great War,
with its 500,000 deaths,
and his 900,000 maimed victims should be rewarded in proportion to his sacrifice.
Orlando,
upon his return from Italy,
is dismissed.
He got nothing.
All of this contributed to creating a context in Italy that nationalists exploited.
shouting about a mutilated victory.
However,
She wasn't.
because Italy had more than it needed to ensure the security of its borders.
The peace conference is in full swing.
The committees work in the offices at the Quai d'Orsay.
On the other side of the bridge,
Place de la Concorde,
Crayon's hotel.
Wilson established his headquarters there and worked with his hundreds of advisors on the great work of his life.
the League of Nations.
In the living rooms,
We start from the principles of the 14 points to develop this pact of the League of Nations.
For Wilson,
The stakes are clear.
He wants to redefine a new world order.
He arrives in Paris with the idea that peace must be made between equals.
He wants a League of Nations that will ensure that the First World War is the last of all wars.
There is a conception of Europe,
These Europeans have a long history.
They have somewhat outdated ideas about peace and war.
This explains why these Europeans are always at war.
We must therefore put an end to these incessant wars which are due to poorly organized and unjust peace agreements.
He wanted to win for the United States this role of world arbiter.
From mid-January to the end of March,
We only talk about the League of Nations.
It's the idea of ​​bringing people together.
All nations within an institution like the UN,
This predates the UN.
and the idea that before declaring war,
We must announce that we are going to declare war and initiate arbitration proceedings.
negotiation.
To avoid these secret agreements,
these secret alliances that generate war,
We need to put in place an organization that is ready to ensure lasting peace.
During the conference in Paris,
all those who fought
Indians,
Indochinese,
Africans are demanding their share of self-determination as a reward for services rendered in millions of deaths and to follow Wilson's principles on the right of peoples to self-determination.
A diver from the ritual attempts unsuccessfully to gain access to the conference.
He is Indochinese.
This is the future Ho Chi Minh.
At the end of March,
Wilson eventually presented his League of Nations to the press.
making it the very heart of the future Treaty of Versailles.
Clemenceau and Lloyd George are polite,
Nothing more.
And the American Congress will never ratify the League of Nations.
from which Germany will be excluded initially.
The Treaty of Versailles was stillborn.
It was a truncated Treaty of Versailles that we had to deal with from the moment America had no presence in the League of Nations institutions.
In parallel, the International Labour Office was created,
which still exists
to secure the emerging working class.
and fight against unemployment and poverty.
But the Allies are playing a dangerous game by maintaining a food blockade in Germany.
This blockade is dividing the Council of
Four.
"Not only are we sowing the seeds of hatred for the future,
We are nurturing a revolution!
This future hatred that Lloyd George speaks of,
visionary,
and the terror of a red revolution that could spread to Germany and the West,
they are speeding up the discussions.
The fate of the former German empire must be settled quickly.
Eventually,
The conference will settle the peace with Germany in one month.
Orlando has left.
and symbolically,
We leave the Quai d'Orsay for the private mansion of an American banker.
Each side wants to derive the best provisions for the future of its country from the peace treaty.
Then the conversations become tense,
because the interests are so divergent.
The British,
they want to maintain,
obviously,
their power,
to maintain their empire,
this empire on which the sun never sets.
They are in favor of a firm stance towards Germany.
And like the French,
They want reparations.
They want an extremely large sum in compensation.
They are even,
initially,
more demanding than the French.
They want the Germans,
in these repairs,
reimburse the war portions.
The French,
them,
are obsessed with their borders and have no choice but to take a very hard line.
Clemenceau will constantly negotiate in order to obtain that
The British and Americans pledge to ensure the security of France.
We must not forget that the issue is primarily demographic.
France has 40 million inhabitants and Germany still has approximately 65 million inhabitants.
Because of this Franco-German inequality,
France's security depends on...
leveling of opportunities,
Therefore, an extremely harsh treaty is needed.
Germany must pay.
Germany needs to be weakened.
So this absolute conviction that Germany is responsible for the war and that for this it must pay,
Bosch will pay.
French and British statesmen knew that they had to make people pay.
and Germany,
themselves being ruined.
And what's even more important,
The reason is that the people were demanding exemplary peace.
They wanted a peace between victors,
where Germany was to be singled out as solely responsible for the war.
And to a gentle peace,
Neither Clemenceau nor Lloyd George would have survived politically.
The French will do everything they can to ensure that the issue...
The issue of security is at the heart of the debates for one simple reason, ultimately.
that is, whatever the outcome of the peace treaties,
France will continue to have a continental border with Germany.
This is not the case for Great Britain.
This is not the case in the United States.
For his part,
Wilson clings to his idea of ​​a just peace.
Our biggest mistake would be to give Germany powerful reasons to seek revenge one day.
They must understand that the occupation of Germany,
at least for 15 years,
will prevent them from complying with the treaty.
I need those 15 years.
He gets them.
Later,
Clemenceau was then able to call French President Poincaré from his office to announce the news.
Miss,
the Presidency of the Republic,
Please.
Mr. President,
I am 15 years old.
Peace has been made.
The clauses of the treaty are being refined.
We will destroy part of the weaponry and reduce the German army to 100,000 men.
NOW,
We need to act quickly.
Early May,
The Germans are summoned to the Trianon hotel in Versailles.
Gentlemen!
This is neither the time nor the place for superfluous talk.
Before you are representatives of the nations that united to resist a war that was imposed upon us for more than four years in a most cruel manner.
Do you want peace?
We are willing to grant it to you.
Here is the book containing our provisions.
The Treaty of Versailles,
That's 400 clauses.
These 400 clauses are very harsh for Germany.
She acknowledges that Germany will lose part of its territory.
Germany will have to pay war reparations.
because she is the one responsible for the war.
But all of that,
It happened in a particular context.
We know the identity of the hater,
because we are there.
We know the intensity of the hatred we are facing.
We have heard the impassioned demands of the victors who claim to make us pay as if we were the vanquished.
and punish us as guilty.
But we are not solely responsible.
The imperialism of European countries has shaped the international situation.
But we are not the only ones to blame.
The imperialism of European countries has poisoned the international situation.
Any other observations?
The meeting is adjourned.
No negotiations.
15 days to respond,
See you in early June.
Indeed,
The Treaty of Versailles is very harsh.
but it would have been difficult for public opinion to accept a treaty that was not.
Germany had to pay.
Once the conditions are known,
in Berlin,
It's outrage.
The way in which the German delegation was treated is considered unacceptable.
We feel betrayed by Wilson.
who had promised a dignified and just peace.
If he hadn't said "with me everything will be different" and the outcome ultimately wasn't different,
He created such an illusion that he created a desire for revenge which was maintained by the German military who hid from their people that it was they who had requested the armistice and not the civilian power.
But from the moment the allies impose peace conditions on a republic that the people have not been able to negotiate.
Well,
The German people feel betrayed by the Weimar Republic.
For the Germans,
And we understand them.
The Treaty of Versailles is a diktat.
It was precisely because the victors could not reach an agreement that all these preliminaries were so lengthy.
too long,
and that at one point,
Public opinion was somewhat there,
that it was necessary to put an end to it,
that it was still necessary to sign this treaty,
Well, we impose it on the vanquished.
And at the same time,
seen from the other side,
This is the ultimate humiliation.
Germany is traumatized.
From his point of view,
She did not lose the war and does not feel responsible.
She is overwhelmed by its 400 clauses and takes time to respond.
In June 1919,
Wilson has had enough.
He wants to return to the United States.
Clemenceau threatens to break the armistice.
Foch is already bringing out his staff maps.
Finally,
June 28th,
The treaty is signed.
in Versailles.
Eventually,
The three negotiators got what they wanted.
Wilson imposed his League of Nations.
Lloyd George obtains the fleet and part of the German colonies.
and Clemenceau secured his borders.
But what the Allies underestimated with the staging and content of the Treaty of Versailles,
It is the profound psychological impact that it will have afterwards.
Humiliation is not the goal.
But humiliation will be the result.
The humiliation is not intentional.
The aim is to make Germany understand that it cannot,
that she must not do it again.
However,
Was it a bad treaty?
Versailles has frozen.
The Treaty of Versailles in 1919 was a major dilemma from the outset.
On one hand,
There was the prospect of building a better world.
And that,
That was Wilson's wish.
And on the other hand,
There was the ambition of the British and the French to divide the world according to their own criteria.
The trauma experienced by all European peoples is such that the peace treaty is probably not a good treaty.
but that it was perhaps the least bad treaty that could be negotiated at that time,
under those conditions.
The treaty was no more unjust than any other treaty that had resulted in a victory.
If the Germans,
at the time,
had not been so crazy,
They should have understood that the Peace of Versailles was a reasonable peace.
But I can only conclude that the war had truly driven them mad.
Following the Treaty of Versailles,
Four more treaties will follow.
They are said to be from the Paris region.
Saint-Germain-en-Laye,
which determines the fate of Austria.
The Trianon at Versailles for Hungary,
Neuilly, where Bulgaria loses part of its territory and access to the sea,
and Sèvres, which will decide the future of the Ottoman Empire.
All these treaties profoundly changed the face of this old Europe of empires.
States are gradually organizing themselves and peace is slowly making its way.
For nearly ten years,
Europe will become an extraordinary laboratory.
The treaties are becoming more flexible.
German industry is recovering, and the first Franco-German partnership in history,
Aristide Briand and Gustav Stressmann,
win the Nobel Peace Prize in 1926.
In Germany,
the Weimar Republic,
thanks to American capital,
regains confidence.
Relations with the neighbors are easing.
We almost forget Versailles and its dictates.
It would be a mistake to think that it's the treaty,
its humiliation and its clauses which nourished the breeding ground of German Nazism and Italian Fascism.
and driving to the worst.
I don't think we can accuse the Treaty of Versailles of planting the seeds that caused the Second World War to explode.
In 1929,
France and Germany were considering the establishment of a customs union and the idea of ​​creating the United States of Europe.
In Europe,
There was no threat of war.
A far more devastating event sweeps away this somewhat dark legend.
The financial crisis,
then the American economic crisis of 1929.
will plunge Europe back into crisis,
still recovering,
and more specifically Germany,
in chaos.
She is the one responsible for the war that threatens.
She's the one who's going to create unemployment.
misery and instilling fear.
Fear of communism,
on the other hand,
of the insurrection.
And to give rise to a radical ideology that will resurrect the resentment and revenge of a peace that cannot be accepted.
In Italy,
Mussolini used Versailles,
But that is not the reason for the rise of fascism.
Mussolini had said from the beginning that the Treaty of Versailles should be reviewed and modified.
From 1921 onwards,
There has been a backlash against the communist party which is planning a revolution.
like the one Lenin did.
Fascism was not supported by major industrialists.
but by the smallest manufacturers,
as he had been supported by the large landowners who had feared being expropriated by the Communist Party.
That is why these small industrialists helped the rise of fascism by supporting a government that promised to enforce order.
Fear of Bolshevism,
an exacerbated desire for order,
humiliation of a bad peace.
The same mechanism was put in place a few years later with the rise of the Nazis.
Hitler's initial success in those crisis years of the 1920s came at precisely the moment when people in Germany were beginning to take a massive interest in the First World War again.
The Treaty of Versailles will once again take center stage.
serving as a pretext for impeccable propaganda.
Hitler promised from the beginning that he would repair the peace of shame.
who will restore the honor of the soldiers and will go and reconquer the lost homeland.
He wants to build monuments for the defeated soldiers.
And the war wounded will receive all the honors they did not receive from the Weimar Republic.
That was it.
Hitler's promise.
Of course Versailles has a connection with Hitler.
Of course Versailles has a link with the Second World War.
But Versailles was not the cause of the Second World War.
Corporal Hitler,
who only feels comfortable within the army,
will make the Treaty of Versailles his personal obsession.
In his madness,
His goal is to end this war that the Germans interrupted on November 11, 1918.
in undignified conditions.
By systematically trampling on the treaty clauses regarding rearmament and the annexation of the Sudetenland and Austria,
it triggers,
on a pretext,
World War II.
After a strange war lasting nearly nine months,
France was soundly defeated in less than five weeks.
It is very clear that Hitler,
in 1940,
won World War I.
Hitler was never as popular in Germany as he was when he defeated France in
1940.
The Treaty of Versailles is in its final hours.
When Pétain,
heroes of Verdun
in turn calls for an armistice.
The date is June 22, 1940.
Hitler demands the Rotonde railway carriage.
In the symbolism of the armistice,
We need to revisit the Armistice of Rotonde and completely censor what happened on November 11, 1918, by having the French sign it in a completely reversed position.
an armistice in the same place,
under the same conditions,
etc.
As much
1918 was secret,
1940 was a huge fuss.
Hitler will immediately demand that the carriage be moved out.
to put it where it was in 1918,
and he will want to sit in Marshal Foch's place on June 21st.
when he will have General Keitel read the armistice conditions.
Ah, so Hitler remembered.
and he is drunk with joy,
who rejoices.
It's humiliation in reverse.
It's revenge.
It's a childish act of revenge.
a spoiled brat's revenge
in dramatic conditions, of course.
The clear ones will be sent to Berlin to be displayed in a grand museum.
the wagon,
the sacred slab,
the monument to the Alsatians and Lorrainers.
But not the statue of Marshal Fulch, which would remain desperately in Compiègne to look at a completely empty clearing since he blew up the museum in July 1940.
Nothing will be left.
The Second World War ended in 1945 with the surrender and total collapse of the Third Reich.
With Germany's defeat,
This is the true end of the war.
started in 1914.
Yet,
almost 80 years after the Sarajevo attack,
in the same place,
History, in its deadly form, repeats itself.
At the time of the Treaties of Versailles and Saint-Germain,
The Allies,
believing they could solve the problem of the Balkan powder keg,
created Yugoslavia.
But the game is rigged from the start.
In this first Yugoslavia on a war tour,
It is the King of Serbia who becomes King of the Serbs.
Croats and Slovenes.
And in fact,
Yugoslavia is described as a Greater Serbia.
During World War II,
Cracks are appearing within Yugoslavia.
Croatian nationalism,
Hitler's ally,
is responsible for a true genocide.
But the communists resisted, led by...
Tito, who quickly established himself as a charismatic leader.
He was the one who would create the great socialist Yugoslavia after the war.
distant satellite of Moscow.
It was he who,
thanks to his grip,
managed to put a lid on the nationalisms within his federation.
Tito had an extraordinary opportunity to establish himself in a Yugoslav territory where everyone is against everyone else.
lid that lasted until his death
in 1980 and which finally collapsed after the fall of communism.
Everyone told us that after the fall of communism,
There will be good things for everyone.
that democracy finally arrives in Bosnia and Herzegovina.
The first free and democratic elections took place in November 1990.
In general opinion,
Nationalist and ultranationalist parties win almost everything.
Serbian nationalist Milosevic seizes power amidst an economic and social crisis.
which immediately generated identity tensions and was ordered in April 1992,
from the hills of Sarajevo,
deadly bombings on the city.
This bridge also served as a demarcation bridge between two parts during the last war in Bosnia and Herzegovina.
On one side, it was the Serbs who controlled the hills and the rest,
And on that side, obviously, it was the inhabitants of Sarajevo.
I'm not going to talk about the Serbs,
Croats and Bosnians,
I am going to live with the inhabitants of Sarajevo who lived on that side of the island.
It was the Mijeska River that divided the Serbs from the rest of the population of Sarajevo.
We've already started talking about them and about us.
The siege of Sarajevo would be the longest in all of modern history and would result in nearly 100,000 deaths and 2 million refugees.
After almost four years of deadlock and a clear failure of the European Union,
the Americans...
as with the two world wars,
intervened forcefully to end the conflict with the Dayton Accords.
They will play again,
as Wilson had dreamed,
the world's police.
On the surface,
The city has been more or less rebuilt and the material damage repaired.
But the wounds and psychological trauma to society are far more considerable.
It will take some time to heal and overcome them.
Some people talk about it as if it happened yesterday, and it's still very much present in everyday conversations.
But nearly 25 years later,
The plain is not closed off.
This symbol of the city,
the library,
which represented both the splendor of the Austro-Hungarian Empire and the multiculturalism of the pre-1914 era, and was destroyed during the war,
houses a plaque that perpetuates intra-community tensions.
I call this plaque the plaque of hate.
I think this plaque is a testament to the suffering in Bosnia and Herzegovina.
It bears witness to our difficult lives today.
How can we build a dialogue?
when you are considered,
but all,
globally,
as criminals.
How to rebuild the Balkans after the first conflagration of 1914,
A serene and peaceful region?
What if it happened again?
Bosnia and Herzegovina,
Today,
continues to be a country with multiple identities.
I'm not sure there won't be a war in Bosnia and Herzegovina.
because for more than a quarter of a century,
Bosnia and Herzegovina is preparing for war.
Here,
Everything is done to make me consider the other person as an enemy and not as a friend.
Bosnia and Herzegovina of the present day,
It is a Bosnia-Herzegovina that draws on history for reasons and pretexts for future fighting.
And that,
It's a vicious cycle.
And if the European Union,
a century later,
could have been the ultimate lid,
The integration solution?
I don't know if the European Union is the solution.
But it definitely represents hope.
And that's something the people here need more than anything else.
In the future,
I really hope to live another thirty years.
Forty years of peace.
The First World War definitively destroyed the hegemony and power of Europe.
Europe has not recovered from the First World War.
Europe ceases to be the dominant power on a global scale and is replaced by the United States.
This marks the end of an era when Europe dominated the world.
Following the First World War,
All European peoples belong to the camp of the vanquished.
The Treaty of Versailles and the fragile peace that accompanied it
were both the seeds and the scapegoats of 20th-century conflicts.
Some fundamental principles remain.
a philosophy,
which were recycled into the foundations of post-war European construction.
European integration,
It's worth what it's worth today.
She has all the weaknesses we know her for,
but it is the only region in the world that has reached this point of integration.
Unite or die.
And perhaps we could create a more visionary Europe.
more humane.
and broader in scope and which would have no requirement for domination,
then she could emerge again, and in a different way, in this world.
A Europe that is searching for itself and that must adapt to new global challenges if it wants to occupy a place on the unstable world stage.